Alfred H. Nolle papers 90.200.Faculty.1980.Nolle
University Archives, Texas State University
Alfred H. Nolle papers
1881-1978, undated
University Archives, Texas State University https://www.univarchives.txstate.edu/
Nolle, Alfred Henry
90.200.Faculty.1980.Nolle
6.6 Linear Feet 11 legal Hollinger boxes, 1 half legal Hollinger box, 16 books.
The Alfred H. Nolle papers document the education and professional activities of Alfred H. Nolle including his roles as German language and literature professor, Dean of Southwest Texas State Teachers College, and member of a number of professional and educational organizations. Topics include higher education administration, foreign language education, teacher education, education accreditation, German language and literature, educational honor societies, professional organizations, the life and career of Lyndon B. Johnson, and the history and administration of Southwest Texas State College and its predecessors.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection has some restrictions. Two gradebook are included dated 1912-1914 and 1920-1921. Access is restricted for 100 years since creation, available in 2022. All other materials open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Dr. Wilson B. Nolle, Alfred H. Nolle's son, in 1980.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged into eight series:
Series I: Graduate education coursework, 1912-1917, undated, 0.16 Linear feet
Series II: Teaching materials, 1918-1947, undated, 0.13 Linear feet
Series III: Administrative records, 1920-1977, undated, 0.85 Linear feet
Series IV: Organizational records and publications, 1912-1976 undated, 3.19 Linear feet
Series V: Event printed material and speeches, 1908-1977, undated, 0.42 Linear feet
Series VI: Miscellaneous publications, 1881-1978, 1.50 Linear feet
Series VII: Newspapers and clippings, 1921-1977, undated, 0.33 Linear feet
Series VIII: Photographs, before 1919-1970, undated, 0.02 Linear feet (14 photographs)
Biographical note
Alfred Henry Nolle was born on April 28, 1889 in St. Charles, Missouri to Louis E. H. Nolle and Mary Wilhelmine Boenker Nolle. Nolle graduated from the University of Missouri in 1911 receiving both a Bachelor of Science in Education and a Bachelor of Arts with honors in German. He completed his M.A. at the University of the South (Sewanee) in 1912 and his Ph.D. in German Literature at University of Pennsylvania in 1915. While at the University of Pennsylvania, Nolle received the Joseph G. Rosengarten Traveling Scholarship in Germanics While traveling and studying in Germany in the summer of 1913, he met his future wife Berda Stewart Wilson. They were married on August 16, 1916. Nolle's dissertation, The German Drama on the St. Louis Stage, was published by the University of Pennsylvania in 1917.
Upon receiving his Ph.D., Nolle returned to the University of Missouri and served as an instructor in Germanic languages for four years, 1915 through 1919. He began teaching German at Southwest Texas State Normal College in 1919 and was the first staff member to hold a Ph.D. By 1923, Nolle was appointed Dean of the Faculty, although he continued teaching while serving as an administrator. In 1936, Nolle was appointed Dean of the College.
Early in his career at Southwest Texas State, Dr. Nolle formed a relationship with future U.S. Senator and U.S. President Lyndon B. Johnson. The two corresponded until Johnson's death and Nolle maintained an interest in following Johnson's political career.
Dr. Nolle served in a number of educational organizations during his career. At Southwest Texas State Teachers College, he served as the sponsor of extra-curricular clubs devoted to studying the German language, including Die Germanistische Gesellschaft and Der Schiller Verein. Nolle served as a member of the Committee on Standards and Classification of the Association of Texas Colleges from 1923 to 1959 and was chair of the committee from 1939 to 1959. He was also involved in the founding of the Scholarship Societies of Texas which became Alpha Chi, a national honor society. Nolle served as president of the organization in 1927 and then as secretary-treasurer from 1928 through 1969.
For his contributions to education in Texas, Nolle received the honorary degree in Doctor of Laws from the East Texas Baptist College in 1957. Dr. Nolle had served as Dean for 37 years, before retiring in 1959, although he continued to work on campus as the secretary-treasurer of Alpha Chi for another decade. He died on March 7, 1979 in San Marcos, Texas.
Sources: Alpha Chi seeks to honor Alfred H. Nolle, San Marcos Daily Record, September 20, 1989; United States Census, 1910; University of Pennsylvania, Proceedings of Commencement, June 16, 1915; Alfred Henry Nolle draft registration card, June 5, 1917, United States World War I Draft Registration Cards, 1917-1918; The records themselves.
General
Index Terms: These materials are indexed under the following headings in the Albert B. Alkek Library's online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings. Persons: Nolle, Alfred Henry; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Evans, C. E. (Cecil Evans). Organizations: Alpha Chi; American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education; American Association of Teachers Colleges; Association of Texas Colleges; Southwest Texas State Normal College; Southwest Texas State Teachers College; Southwest Texas State College. Subjects: German language; Language and education; Education, Higher—Administration; Teachers colleges; Teachers--Training of. Formats: (Genre Forms) Business correspondence; Conference papers and proceedings; Course materials; Examinations; Minutes (records); Personal correspondence; Reference works; Speeches.
Related Materials
The University Archives holds additional materials related to German clubs and to the honor society Alpha Chi. Please contact us for additional information on accessing these records.
Materials related to accreditation of the University can be found within Texas Education Agency reports, National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education reports, and Southern Association of Colleges and Schools reports. Finding aids for these collections are available online through the University Archives Digital Collections webpage.
The University Archives also holds back issues of the student-run newspaper, The University Star, and its predecessors, The College Star and The Normal Star. Early issues of the paper have been digitized and are available through the University Archives web site. Issues of the University's yearbook, Pedagog, may also contain related information. These have also been digitized and are available on the University Archives web site.
Scope and Contents
The Alfred H. Nolle papers document the education and professional activities of Alfred H. Nolle including his roles as German language and literature professor, Dean of Southwest Texas State Teachers College, and member of a number of professional and educational organizations. Materials include incoming correspondence, outgoing correspondence, speeches, reports, manuscripts, graduate coursework, theses, lecture notes, assignments, exams, invitations, event programs, accreditation reports, surveys, meeting proceedings, meeting minutes, publications, newspapers, newspaper clippings, and photographs. Although items within the collection date from 1881 through 1978, the majority date from Nolle's career at Southwest Texas State Normal School/Southwest Texas State Teachers College through his retirement, from 1919 through 1978. Topics include higher education administration, foreign language education, teacher education, education accreditation, German language and literature, educational honor societies, professional organizations, the life and career of Lyndon B. Johnson, and the history and administration of Southwest Texas State College and its predecessors.
Separated Materials
Publications with call numbers are housed off site and may be requested in the reading room.
Printed materials related to the inauguration of Southwest Texas State Teachers College President J. Garland Flowers in 1943, including a program, luncheon program, invitation, and RSVP card, were separated into the existing collection of Presidential inauguration records. Additionally, seven baccalaureate and commencement programs dating from 1913 through 1938 were separated into the existing collection Commencement records.
Twenty five complete issues of the newspaper The College Star dating from 1928 through 1973 were separated into the Student newspaper collection. Additionally, during previous processing, all newspaper clippings were photocopied and then destroyed.
Division of Personnel records and correspondence were destroyed as they included restricted information regarding student grades and expulsions.
Index Terms
Subjects
Teachers colleges; Teachers -- Training of
Places
German language; Language and education; Education, Higher -- Administration
Subjects (Persons)
Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Evans, C. E. (Cecil Eugene)
- Graduate education coursework, 1912-1917, undated; 0.16 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Alfred H. Nolle received his M.A. and Ph.D. studying German language and literature. Materials within this series document Nolle's graduate education and date from 1912 through 1917 with some undated items. They include a manuscript copy of his Master's thesis, A Comparative Study of Maler Müller's "Golo und Genoveva" and Tieck's "Leben und Tod der heiligen Genoveva." The thesis compares German works related to the medieval heroine Genevieve of Brabant. Notes and handouts from his doctoral course work are also included documenting courses on English philology and changes to the German language. Additionally, some notes for an unspecified course are in Icelandic. Also found within this series are two published copies of his Ph.D. thesis, The German Drama on the St. Louis Stage. The thesis explores the varied success of German theaters in St. Louis, Missouri in the 19th and early 20th centuries.
  - M.A. thesis manuscript, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Course notes and handouts, 1913-1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Published Ph.D. thesis, The German Drama on the St. Louis Stage, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Teaching materials, 1918-1947, undated; 0.13 Linear Feet
  Nolle served as an instructor and professor of German language and literature from his time in graduate school through his retirement at Southwest Texas State Teacher College in 1959. The materials found within this series document Nolle's instruction in courses on German language and literature and include: course offerings, lecture notes, course outlines, assignments, quizzes, and exams. The majority of the assignments and exams are translation exercises.
  - Teaching materials, 1918-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Teaching materials, 1934-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Teaching materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Teaching materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grade book, 1912-1914 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Grade book, 1920-1921 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Administrative records, 1920-1977, undated; 0.85 Linear Feet
  The correspondence within this series was isolated and organized chronologically by a previous processor. This organization was kept although correspondence is also found within the series Organizational records. Additional administrative records within the series are organized alphabetically by subject.
  The Administrative records series documents the career of Alfred H. Nolle as an educator and college administrator. Records within this series include incoming correspondence, copies of outgoing correspondence, reports, statistics, short writings by Nolle and others, proposals, pamphlets, and meeting minutes. The majority of the correspondents include administrators and faculty from other universities. Congratulatory correspondence to Nolle on receipt of his honorary Doctor of Laws degree from East Texas Baptist College is included. Correspondence to and from Lyndon B. Johnson and concerning Johnson's relationship with Nolle and the College are also found within the series. Topics of the correspondence and records include the administration of Southwest Texas State Normal Collages and Southwest Texas State Teachers College, the accreditation of the college, academic standards, foreign language education, curriculum, College faculty, the Religious Activities Council, and San Marcos and its schools. Although records within this series date to after Nolle's retirement from Southwest Texas State College, the majority of the materials relate to the College and to the organizations.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, East Texas Baptist College commencement, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, East Texas Baptist College commencement, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Lyndon B. Johnson, 1955-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Lyndon B. Johnson, 1965-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Curriculum and language requirements, reports and statistics, 1924-1928, 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Deans and Testing Officers, Texas State Teachers Colleges, meeting minutes, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - President C. E. Evans materials, 1936, 1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Faculty pamphlets, 1952, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty reports and statistics, 1931-circa 1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - President J. Garland Flowers oral history, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - German clubs history, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - German student (former) manuscripts, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson's Days at SWTSC press releases, 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Nolle curriculum vitae and career notes, 1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nolle faculty identification card, Southwest Texas State University, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Nolle writings on education and administration, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Religious Activities Council records, 1929-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Religious Activities Council records, 1944-1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - San Marcos schools advisory committee records, 1940, 1950-1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - San Marcos, Texas proposed city charter, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Southwest Texas State College history, 1964, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Status of Women Committee reports, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Student-Faculty-Administration Board proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Navy V-1 program flier, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Organizational records, 1912-1976 undated; 3.19 Linear Feet
  Records are arranged alphabetically by organization, then by record type and date.
  Alfred H. Nolle was involved with a number of national, state, and local organizations in his capacity as a graduate student, a professor of German, and as an educational administrator. These organizations included honor societies, professional organizations, student organizations, and state agencies. The materials within this series reflect Nolle's interactions these organizations including his role obtaining accreditations for the Southwest Texas State Teachers College as Dean of Faculty and his active role as secretary-treasurer of Alpha Chi honor society. Materials include accreditation reports, surveys, meeting proceedings, meeting minutes, speeches, membership lists, correspondence, publications, educational and institutional standards, and organizational histories and rituals. Topics include organizational membership, meetings, events, language education, teacher education, and the extension work of the College. Historical information about the College is also present within drafts of reports for accreditation including faculty size, faculty education, staff salaries, library resources, admission requirements, and graduation standards.
  - Alpha Chi constitution and meeting proceedings, 1935-1956 (Volume LB2338 .S37 1922-56)
  - Alpha Chi records, 1935-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Alpha Chi records, 1966-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Alpha Chi Recorder, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education records, 1948-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education records, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education published manuals and standards, 1949, 1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1926-1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1933-1936 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1939-1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges accreditation reports, 1945-1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges records, 1926-1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges records, 1931-1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges records, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges records, 1940-1944 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges standards and surveys, 1926, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges standards and surveys, 1927-1938 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - American Association of Teacher Colleges standards and surveys, 1939-1948 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Association of College Honor Societies information booklet and minutes, 1963, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1916-1932 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1931-1938 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Association of Texas Colleges proceedings, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Association of Texas Colleges records, 1946, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board of Regents, Texas State Teachers Colleges reports, 1949, 1957, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Delta Alpha Epsilon records, 1934, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Missouri Society of Teachers of Modern Languages [TYPE], 1916-1917 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education reports and responses, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha of Missouri directory, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Phi Delta Kappa directory and speech, 1912, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Pi Gamma Mu records, 1936-1942, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Scholia records, 1928-1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Scholarship Societies of the South minutes and constitution, 1931-1934 (Volume LB2338 .S37 1922-56)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools records, 1929-1946 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools published history, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Southern Council on Teacher Education manuscript, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - State Commission on School Accreditation mintues, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - State Department of Education, Aviation Education in Texas Public Schools, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - State Department of Education, Laws, Rules and Regulations Governing State Teachers' Certificates, 1929, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - State Department of Education report on Southwest Texas State Teachers College, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - State Department of Education reports of extension work, 1934-1947 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - State Department of Education, Texas Public Schools Standards and Activities of the Division of Supervision, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - State Department of Education, Texas Public Schools Standards and Activities of the Division of Supervision, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Texas Association of German Students, TAGS newsletter, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Event speeches and printed materials, 1908-1977, undated; 0.42 Linear Feet
  Arranged by type of material and then by date.
  As Dean of Faculty at Southwest Texas State Teachers College and as a member of a number of professional organizations, Dr. Nolle served as a representative of the College and as an authority on education administration. In the course of those duties, Nolle attended and gave speeches at a number of events including commencement ceremonies, presidential inaugurations, awards banquets and organizational meetings. Materials within this series include event and meeting programs, speeches by Nolle, speeches by others or by unidentified speakers, invitations to events, and RSVP cards. These materials date 1916 through 1977. Also included is a small collection of programs that predate Nolle's tenure at Southwest Texas State Normal School. Dating from 1906 through 1916, they include commencement programs and programs for a commencement event, "Deutscher Abend" or German Evening, which included singing and a play performed by students studying German.
  - Speeches, 1936-1954 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, 1957-1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Speeches by others, 1950- 1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1908-1916 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1916-1942 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Programs, 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Programs, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Invitations, 1942-1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Invitations, 1961-1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous publications, 1881-1978; 1.50 Linear Feet
  Due to the wide range of topics represented in the series, works are organized chronologically.